One of the things that might
help speed up your
learning algorithm
is to slowly reduce your
learning rate over time.
We call this
learning rate decay.
Let's see how you
can implement this.
Let's start with an
example of why you
might want to implement
learning rate decay.
Suppose you're implementing
mini-batch gradient descents
with a reasonably
small mini-batch,
maybe a mini-batch has
just 64, 128 examples.
Then as you iterate,
your steps will be a
little bit noisy and
it will tend towards
this minimum over here,
but it won't exactly converge.
But your algorithm might
just end up wandering
around and never really converge
because you're using
some fixed value for
Alpha and there's
just some noise
in your different mini-batches.
But if you were to
slowly reduce your
learning rate Alpha,
then during the initial phases,
while your learning rate
Alpha is still large,
you can still have
relatively fast learning.
But then as Alpha gets smaller,
your steps you take will be
slower and smaller, and so,
you end up oscillating in
a tighter region around
this minimum rather than
wandering far away even as
training goes on and on.
The intuition behind
slowly reducing
Alpha is that maybe during the
initial steps of learning,
you could afford to
take much bigger steps,
but then as learning
approaches convergence,
then having a slower
learning rate
allows you to take
smaller steps.
Here's how you can implement
learning rate decay.
Recall that one epoch is
one pass through the data.
If you have a training
set as follows,
maybe break it up into
different mini-batches.
Then the first pass through
the training set is
called the first epoch,
and then the second pass is
the second epoch, and so on.
One thing you could do is set
your learning rate Alpha to be
equal to 1 over 1
plus a parameter,
which I'm going to
call the decay rate,
times the epoch num.
This is going to be times some
initial learning rate Alpha 0.
Note that the decay
rate here becomes
another hyperparameter which
you might need to tune.
Here's a concrete example.
If you take several epochs,
so several passes
through your data,
if Alpha 0 is equal to
0.2 and the decay
rate is equal to 1,
then during your first epoch,
Alpha will be 1 over 1
plus 1 times Alpha 0,
so your learning
rate will be 0.1.
That's just evaluating
this formula
when the decay rate is equal
to 1 and epoch num is 1.
On the second epoch,
your learning rate
decay is 0.67.
On the third, 0.5.
On the fourth, 0.4, and so on.
Feel free to evaluate more of
these values yourself
and get a sense
that as a function
of epoch number,
your learning rate
gradually decreases,
according to this
formula up on top.
If you wish to use
learning rate decay,
what you can do is
try a variety of
values of both
hyperparameter Alpha 0,
as well as this decay
rate hyperparameter,
and then try to find a
value that works well.
Other than this formula
for learning rate decay,
there are a few other
ways that people use.
For example, this is
called exponential decay,
where Alpha is equal to
some number less than 1,
such as 0.95, times
epoch num times Alpha 0.
This will exponentially quickly
decay your learning rate.
Other formulas that people
use are things like
Alpha equals some constant
over epoch num square
root times Alpha 0,
or some constant k and
another hyperparameter over
the mini-batch number t
square rooted times Alpha 0.
Sometimes you also see people
use a learning rate that
decreases and discretes that,
where for some number of steps,
you have some learning rate,
and then after a while,
you decrease it by
one-half, after a while,
by one-half, after a while,
by one-half, and so,
this is a discrete staircase.
So far, we've talked about using
some formula to
govern how Alpha,
the learning rate
changes over time.
One other thing that people
sometimes do is manual decay.
If you're training just
one model at a time,
and if your model takes
many hours or even
many days to train,
what some people would do
is just watch your model as
it's training over a
large number of days,
and then now you say, oh,
it looks like the learning
rate slowed down,
I'm going to decrease
Alpha a little bit.
Of course, this works, this
manually controlling Alpha,
really tuning Alpha by hand,
hour-by-hour, day-by-day.
This works only if
you're training
only a small number of models,
but sometimes people
do that as well.
Now you have a few
more options of how to
control the learning rate Alpha.
Now, in case you're
thinking, wow,
this is a lot of
hyperparameters,
how do I select amongst all
these different options?
I would say don't worry about
it for now, and next week,
we'll talk more about how
to systematically
choose hyperparameters.
For me, I would say that
learning rate decay
is usually lower
down on the list
of things I try.
Setting Alpha just a
fixed value of Alpha and
getting that to be well-tuned
has a huge impact,
learning rate decay does help.
Sometimes it can really
help speed up training,
but it is a little
bit lower down
my list in terms of the
things I would try.
But next week, when we talk
about hyperparameter tuning,
you'll see more systematic
ways to organize all of
these hyperparameters and how
to efficiently
search amongst them.
That's it for
learning rate decay.
Finally, I also want
to talk a little bit
about local optima
and saddle points in
neural networks so you can have
a little bit better
intuition about the types of
optimization problems your
optimization algorithm
is trying to solve
when you're trying
to train these neural networks.
Let's go onto the next
video to see that.